<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MHD Turbulence | Forrest Glines</title>
    <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/tag/mhd-turbulence/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://forrestglines.github.io/tag/mhd-turbulence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>MHD Turbulence</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://forrestglines.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>MHD Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/tag/mhd-turbulence/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decaying Magnetized Turbulence in the Taylor-Green Vortex</title>
      <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/project/taylor_green/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://forrestglines.github.io/project/taylor_green/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To investigate the development of turbulence in intermittently driven plasmas
such as the intracluster medium, we used our newly developed K-Athena code to
run a series of simulations of the magnetized Taylor-Green vortex. The
turbulence that arises from the unsteady flow of the magnetized Taylor-Green
vortex models the turbulence that develops from large scale infrequent events
such as galaxy cluster mergers disturbing the intracluster medium. In our
paper, we examine the magnitude and the spectra of the kinetic, magnetic, and
thermal energy reservoirs within the plasma. Additionally, we apply an energy
transfer analysis to study the movement of energy between different length
scale and between different reservoirs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our full setup, explanation, and analysis can be found in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.103.043203&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Physical Review E&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Tower AGN Feedback within Magnetized Galaxy Clusters</title>
      <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/project/magnetic_agn/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://forrestglines.github.io/project/magnetic_agn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My current focus is the development of next-generation simulations of
magnetized galaxy clusters with magnetized active galactic nuclei (AGN)
feedback, done in tandem with development of AthenaPK and Parthenon. High
computational efficiency on CPUs and GPUs enabled by the Parthenon adaptive
mesh refinement framework will allow higher resolution and higher fidelity
simulations than previously possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simulations use realistic gravitational and entropy profiles of galaxy
cluster with a tabulated cooling function. Feedback from AGN is triggered by
cold gas accreted into the AGN and is deposited into the intracluster medium
via thermal heating, precessing kinetic jets, and a magnetic tower.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
