<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 | Forrest Glines</title>
    <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication-type/2/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://forrestglines.github.io/publication-type/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>2</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://forrestglines.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication-type/2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magnetized decaying turbulence in the weakly compressible Taylor-Green vortex </title>
      <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/taylor_green/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/taylor_green/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) turbulence affects both terrestrial and astrophysical
plasmas. The properties of magnetized turbulence must be better understood to
more accurately characterize these systems. This work presents ideal MHD
simulations of the compressible Taylor-Green vortex under a range of initial
subsonic Mach numbers and magnetic field strengths. We find that regardless of
the initial field strength, the magnetic energy becomes dominant over the
kinetic energy on all scales after at most several dynamical times. The
spectral indices of the kinetic and magnetic energy spectra become shallower
than $k^{−5/3}$ over time and generally fluctuate. Using a shell-to-shell energy
transfer analysis framework, we find that the magnetic fields facilitate a
significant amount of the energy flux and that the kinetic energy cascade is
suppressed. Moreover, we observe nonlocal energy transfer from the large-scale
kinetic energy to intermediate and small-scale magnetic energy via magnetic
tension. We conclude that even in intermittently or singularly driven weakly
magnetized systems, the dynamical effects of magnetic fields cannot be
neglected.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental Dependence of Self-regulating Black Hole Feedback in Massive Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/self_regulating_bh_feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/self_regulating_bh_feedback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the universe&amp;rsquo;s most massive galaxies, active galactic
nucleus (AGN) feedback appears to limit star formation. The
accumulation of cold gas near the central black hole fuels
powerful AGN outbursts, keeping the ambient medium in a
state marginally unstable to condensation and formation of
cold gas clouds. However, the ability of that mechanism to
self-regulate may depend on numerous environmental factors,
including the depth of the potential well and the pressure
of the surrounding circumgalactic medium (CGM). Here we
present a suite of numerical simulations, with halo mass
ranging from $2\times10^{12} M_\odot$ to $8\times10^{14} M_\odot$, exploring the
dependence of AGN feedback on those environmental factors.
We include the spatially extended mass and energy input
from the massive galaxy&amp;rsquo;s old stellar population capable of
sweeping gas out of the galaxy if the confining CGM
pressure is sufficiently low. Our simulations show that
this feedback mechanism is tightly self-regulating in a
massive galaxy with a deep central potential and low CGM
pressure, permitting only small amounts of multiphase gas
to accumulate and allowing no star formation. In a
similar-mass galaxy with shallower central potential and
greater CGM pressure the feedback mechanism is more
episodic, producing extended multiphase gas and allowing
small rates of star formation ($\sim0.1 M_\odot \text{yr}^{−1}$). At the
low-mass end, the mechanism becomes implausibly explosive,
perhaps because the CGM initially has no angular momentum,
which would have reduced the amount of condensed gas
capable of fueling feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tests of AGN Feedback Kernels in Simulated Galaxy Clusters </title>
      <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/agn_thermal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/agn_thermal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In cool-core galaxy clusters with central cooling times much shorter than a Hubble time, condensation of the ambient central gas is regulated by a heating mechanism, probably an active galactic nucleus. Previous analytical work has suggested that certain radial distributions of heat input may result in convergence to a quasi-steady global state that does not substantively change on the timescale for radiative cooling, even if the heating and cooling are not locally in balance. To test this hypothesis, we simulate idealized galaxy cluster halos using the ENZO code with an idealized, spherically symmetric heat input kernel intended to emulate. Thermal energy is distributed with radius according to a range of kernels, in which total heating is updated to match total cooling every 10 Myr. Some heating kernels can maintain quasi-steady global configurations, but no kernel we tested produces a quasi-steady state with central entropy as low as those observed in cool-core clusters. The general behavior of the simulations depends on the proportion of heating in the inner 10 kpc, with low central heating leading to central cooling catastrophes, high central heating creating a central convective zone with an inverted entropy gradient, and intermediate central heating resulting in a flat central entropy profile that exceeds observations. The timescale on which our simulated halos fall into an unsteady multiphase state is proportional to the square of the cooling time of the lowest-entropy gas, allowing more centrally concentrated heating to maintain a longer-lasting steady state.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> K-Athena: a performance portable structured grid finite volume magnetohydrodynamics code </title>
      <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/kathena/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/kathena/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Large scale simulations are a key pillar of modern research and require
ever-increasing computational resources. Different novel manycore architectures
have emerged in recent years on the way towards the exascale era. Performance
portability is required to prevent repeated non-trivial refactoring of a code
for different architectures. We combine ATHENA++, an existing
magnetohydrodynamics (MHD) CPU code, with KOKKOS, a performance portable
on-node parallel programming paradigm, into K-ATHENA to allow efficient
simulations on multiple architectures using a single codebase. We present
profiling and scaling results for different platforms including Intel Skylake
CPUs, Intel Xeon Phis, and NVIDIA GPUs. K-ATHENA achieves $&amp;gt; 10^8$ cell-updates/s
on a single V100 GPU for second-order double precision MHD calculations, and a
speedup of 30 on up to 24,576 GPUs on Summit (compared to 172,032 CPU cores),
reaching $1:94\times10^12$ total cell-updates/s at 76 percent parallel efficiency.
Using a roofline analysis we demonstrate that the overall performance is
currently limited by DRAM bandwidth and calculate a performance portability
metric of 62.8 percent. Finally, we present the implementation strategies used
and the challenges encountered in maximizing performance. This will provide
other research groups with a straightforward approach to prepare their own
codes for the exascale era. K-ATHENA is available at
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/pgrete/kathena&#34;&gt;https://gitlab.com/pgrete/kathena&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Relativistic High-Resolution Shock-Capturing for Heterogeneous Computing</title>
      <link>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/scalable_shock_capturing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://forrestglines.github.io/publication/scalable_shock_capturing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A shift is underway in high performance computing (HPC) towards heterogeneous
parallel architectures that emphasize medium and fine grain thread parallelism.
Many scientific computing algorithms, including simple finite-differencing
methods, have already been mapped to heterogeneous architectures with
order-of-magnitude gains in performance as a result. Recent case studies
examining high-resolution shock-capturing (HRSC) algorithms suggest that these
finite-volume methods are good candidates for emerging heterogeneous
architectures. HRSC methods form a key scientific kernel for compressible
inviscid solvers that appear in astrophysics and engineering applications and
tend to require enormous memory and computing resources. This work presents a
case study of an HRSC method executed on a heterogeneous parallel architecture
utilizing hundreds of GPU enabled nodes with remote direct memory access to the
GPUs for a non-trivial shock application using the relativistic
magnetohydrodynamics model.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
